A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, RG 5 Program Files, Subgroup Grant Files FA1795
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, RG 5 Program Files, Subgroup Grant Files
1986-2016
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1795
65.32 Cubic Feet 172 standard letter document boxes.
35.1 Gigabytes
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Arranged in 15 series by program/topic.
Scope and Contents
Grant admininstration files
- Arts and Culture, 1987-2016; 1; 28.1 Cubic Feet 74 letter document boxes
  - American Music Theater Festival, Inc., 87-21, 1987 March 27-1988 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    Knight File Number - 1284
    Scope and Contents
    Grant 87-21, $35,000.00, for an International Symposium on Contemporary Music Theater, planned as an integral part of the fourth Festival season. To encourage the creation, development and production of contemporary music theater of the highest quality.
  - The Columbus Museum Inc., 87-158, 1987 September 25-1988 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1310
    Grant 87-158, $30,000.00, for Phase II of the New Masterpiece Fund of the Columbus Museum.
  - North Carolina Performing Arts Center at Charlotte Foundation, 88-170, 1988 September 21-1989 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1483
    Grant 88-170, $1,000,000.00, for a campaign for a new performiong arts center to serve the Charlotte metropolitan area.
  - Detroit Symphony Orchestra Hall Inc., 88-68, 1988 March 25-1990 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 1331
    Grant 88-68, $500,000, for a challenge grant to eliminate the Orchestra's operating deficit. Knight Foundation supplied the lead gift, to be matched 3:1 within the next two years by contributions or pledges. [KF gave a .5 million dollar endowment grant to the Symphony in early 1997.]
  - Miami City Ballet, 89-45, 1989 March 21-1990 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1443
    Grant 89-45, $250,000.00, for a challenge grant to build a world class production of "The Nutcracker".
  - American Federation of Arts, 89-175, 1989 September 22-1991 September 30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1162
    Grant 89-175, $450,000.00, to develop three touring art exhibitions curated by museums in Knight Foundation cities of interest and to make those exhibitions more accessible in these cities.
  - Florida Philharmonic Orchestra, 90-140, 1990 June 19-1991 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1348
    Grant 90-140, $25,000.00, to support "Pops by the Bay," a summer concert series which has been offered at Miami Marine Stadium since the mid-1960s.
  - Michigan Opera Theatre, 90-209, 1990 September 27-1991 September 30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1446
    Grant 90-209, $500,000.00, for Phase I of the capital campaign for a new opera house (property acquisition and planning).
  - Museum of Discovery and Science Inc., 90-308, 1990 December 18-1991 December 31 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1467
    Grant 90-308, $100,000.00, for a capital grant for a new science center and IMAX theater at this hands-on museum. The Discovery Center offers children an opportunity to explore the wonders of the universe in a user-friendly environment.
  - Arts and Science Council-Charlotte/Mecklenburg Inc., 91-233, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1266
    Grant 91-233, $315,000, to stabilize the operations and programs of the North Carolina Dance Theater, the only professional dance company in the state.
  - Black Archives, History and Research Foundation of South Florida, Inc., 91-360, 1991 December 12-1992 December 12 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1292
    Grant 91-360, $50,000.00, for the restoration of the Lyric Theater the oldest legitimate theater remaining in Miami, listed on the National Register of Historic Places. Upon restoration the 400-seat facility will serve again as a community theater, accommodating smaller performing arts groups, cinema, and educational programs.
  - Columbia Art Association, 91-76, 1991 March 26-1992 March 26 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1195
    Grant 91-76, $75,000.00, for a capital grant to purchase new video and audio equipment to enhance the educational mission of the Gibbs Planetarium.
  - Greater Akron Musical Association, 91-66, 1991 March 26-1992 March 26 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1234
    Grant 91-66, $30,000.00, for the 1991-1992 season.
  - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, 91-214, 1991 September 19-1992 September 19 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1397
    Grant 91-214, $300,000.00, for the Ballet Commissioning Project to choreograph and produce a new work in collaboration with the Pennsylvania Ballet.
  - Milledgeville Baldwin County Allied Arts Inc., 90-211, 1990 September 27-1992 September 30 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1449
    Grant 90-211, $30,000.00, to subsidize general programming for three years, freeing this organization to address its capital needs. To focus on completing the restoration of its arts center and developing new, arts-related, for-profit ventures that will support the goal of being 75% self-supporting, rather than 50%, as it is now.
  - Minnesota Public Radio, 87-272, 1990 September 27-1992 September 30 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1452
    Grant 87-272, $50,000.00, for a series of thirty-five national broadcasts of the Saint Paul Chamber Orchestra 1988-89 season.
  - Spoleto Festival U.S.A, 91-48, 1991 March 26-1992 March 26 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1815
    Grant 91-48, $25,000, to support a city-wide exhibition of place-specific art, in conjunction with Charleston's international arts festival.
  - Twin Cities Public Television Inc., 91-155, 1991 June 20-1992 June 20 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1749
    Grant 91-155, $28,000.00, for the "Focusing on the Future" project, an effort to focus community-wide attention on the options for the future facing Greater St. Paul.
  - City of Saint Paul, 92-49, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1298
    Grant 92-49, $50,000.00, to conduct a study and begin planning a downtown cultural corridor. To be a backbone of a recovery strategy for the city (and especially a downtown) which is in serious economic trouble today. Provide agrressive marketing of a Cultural Capital to draw millions of Minnesotans and out-of-state visitors each year.
  - Film Society of Miami Inc., 92-316, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1345
    Grant 92-316, $20,000.00, for the Tenth Miami Film Festival, known for introducing new talent and cutting edge filmmaking, the Film Society of Miami is committed to presenting outstanding international films to South Florida audiences. The center piece of the society's year-round program is the annual film festival.
  - Minnesota Museum of American Art, 92-36, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1451
    Grant 92-36, $50,000, to consolidate four facilities into a single new museum, to expand the operating endowment and to enhance the collection. 6/01/12: CHANGED TYPE OF SUPPORT CODING FROM ENDOWMENT TO GENERAL OPERATING. GRANT NOT INCLUDED IN ENDOWMENT GRANT REPORTING GOING FORWARD.
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 92-98, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1479
    Grant 92-98, $1,000,000.00, for a demonstration project using historic preservation to revitalize downtowns in three Knight cities. Its mission is to save America's historical environments. Among other things the trust provides technical and financial assistance to community organizations and public agencies for historic preservation programs.
  - The Philharmonic Society of Boulder, 92-186, 1992 September 16-1993 September 16 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1783
    Grant 92-186, $5,000, to help establish a scholarship program for disadvantaged students.
  - San Diego Museum of Art, 92-307, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1816
    Grant 92-307, $75,000, for the development of IMAGE, an interactive computer guide to the museum's collection.
  - Smithsonian Institute, 92-14, 1992 March 25-1993 March 25 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1722
    Grant 92-14, $500,000.00, for construction of the national Museum of the American Indian on the National Mall in Washington, D.C..
  - Spirit Square Arts Center Corporation, 92-217, 1992 June 19-1993 June 19 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1824
    Grant 92-217, $40,000, to equip the Knight Gallery with a dehumidification system and exterior moisture control.
  - Springmaid Villa Art Museum Association, 92-66, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1724
    Grant 92-66, $25,000.00, for construction of a regional art center and museum.
  - Young Audiences of Santa Clara Valley, 92-129, 1992 June 17-1993 June 17 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1770
    Grant 92-129, $20,000, for an arts-in-education project.
  - Detroit Symphony Orchestra Hall Inc., 93-153, 1993 June 15-1994 June 15 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1332
    Grant 93-153, $750,000.00, for an operating stabilizaion initiative. This grant will be paid $250,000 in 1993, $250,000 in 1994 and $250,000 in 1995.
  - Macon Neighborhood Arts Inc, 93-133, 1993 June 15-1994 June 15 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1427
    Grant 93-133, $25,150.00, for a start-up costs for a "Saturday Arts School" for disadvantaged youth living in public housing and surrounding low-income neighborhoods.
  - Meet the Composer, 93-155, 1993 June 15-1994 June 15 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1434
    Grant 93-155, $100,000.00, for the New Residencies program to foster collaboration among artists, arts organizations and community organizations. Founded in 1974, Meet the Composer is a national organization that fosters the creation, performance and recording of music by American composers and develops new audiences for their work. The organization supports composers through commissions, performances, residencies and collaborations.
  - Museum of Discovery and Science, Inc., 93-61, 1993 March 22-1994 March 22 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1468
    Grant 93-61, $50,000.00, for the Youth and Teen Science TRACK, a model science enrichment program for disadvantaged students. It will offer enrichment classes, involvement in museum program planning, career awareness seminars with professional scientists, volunteer opportunities at the museum, and paid summer employment.
  - National Assembly of Local Arts Agencies, 93-150, 1993 June 15-1994 June 15 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1472
    Grant 93-150, $75,000.00, for a pilot program to strengthen local arts agencies in five Knight cities by developing on-site consulting "SWAT Teams" that would analyze the internal organization of the agencies, as well as the climate in which they are operating, and provide recommendations for long-term growth and planning. NALAA will address long-range financial stability public perception, board effectiveness and program development.
  - Public Corporation for the Arts of the City of Long Beach, 93-51, 1993 March 22-1994 March 22 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1821
    Grant 93-51, $10,000, to complete a cultural needs assessment of folk and traditional artists in the region; to develop a registry of traditional artists; and to pilot a folklorist-in-residence program.
  - San Jose Museum of Art Association, 93-152, 1993 June 15-1994 June 15 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1826
    Grant 93-152, $300,000, to initiate a model collection-sharing program with the Whitney Museum of Art.
  - Wichita Symphony Society Inc., 93-22, 1993 March 22-1994 March 22 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1766
    Grant 93-22, $25,000, for touring performances in other Kansas communities during the orchestra's 50th anniversary season.
  - North Carolina Performing Arts Center at Charlotte Foundation, 94-233, 1994 September 20-1995 September 20 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1484
    Grant 94-233, $109,580.00, to plan and implement the pilot stage of an in-house marketing agency to serve the needs of the Performing Arts Center, North Carolina Dance Theatre, Opera Carolina and Charlotte Repertory Theatre.
  - Appalshop Incorporated, 95-30, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1282
    Grant 95-30, $20,000.00, to expand the reach of its community radio station to rural communities in central Appalachia.
  - Boston Symphony Orchestra Inc., 95-111, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1911
    Grant 95-111, $50,000.00, for a "Magic of Music" planning grant for planning activities to enhance youth education and outreach programs as a partner in the Boston Music Education Collaborative.
  - Brooklyn Philharmonic Orchestra, 95-112, 1995 September 18-1996 September 18 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1912
    Grant 95-112, $50,000.00, for a "Magic of Music" planning grant for planning to expand the interplay program series.
  - The Children's Theatre of Charlotte Inc., 95-241, 1995 September 20-1996 September 20 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1300
    Grant 95-241, $35,000.00, to professionalize the development and public relations departments by upgrading the director of development position from part-time to full-time, adding a volunteer coordinator and enhancing marketing and promotional efforts.
  - Cleveland Children's Museum, 95-255, 1995 September 20-1996 September 20 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1920
    Grant 95-255, $50,000.00, to examine the impact of children's museums on schools, families, children and communities.
  - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, 94-75, 1994 March 23-1996 March 23 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1398
    Grant 94-75, $300,000.00, for the Florida Festival, including commissioning and presenting a new work by the Miami City Ballet.
  - Los Angeles Philharmonic Association, 95-119, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 2022
    Grant 95-119, $50,000, for the "Magic of Music" planning grant to test four inter-related pilot programs targeting new audiences.
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 95-202, 1995 September 20-1996 September 20 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 2023
    Grant 95-202, $261,000, for the first phase of the Museum Loan Network, a national program to encourage and support the exchange of art objects among art museums and collecting institutes.
  - Miami Art Museum of Dade County Association Inc. (now Jorge M. Perez Art Museum of Miami Dade), 95-166, 1995 June 20-1996 June 20 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1441
    Grant 95-166, $100,000.00,Jorge M. Perez Art Museum of Miami Dade County Inc. to present the traveling exhibition "Caribbean Visions: Contemporary Painting and Sculpture" and related programming. The show features more than 120 works of art created in the last 50 years, providing a provocative survey of the various cultural traditions that have influenced the art of the Caribbean.
  - Miami Light Project Inc., 95-70, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1445
    Grant 95-70, $25,000.00, for a partnership with the South Florida Art Center and The Field, a national arts service organization, designed to provide local artists with performance, touring and professional development opportunities.
  - New World Symphony Inc., 95-114, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1482
    Grant 95-114, $50,000.00, to develop and test an experimental concert series that will include enhanced educational, social and multi-media activities. For the development of promising ideas for creating a greater sense of excitement in the concert-going experience and more vital relationship between artists and audiences.
  - Oregon Symphony Association, 95-115, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 2025
    Grant 95-115, $50,000, for a Magic of Music planning grant to plan and test two new program concepts that reshape the concert hall environment and experiment with non conventional programming.
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 95-69, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1807
    Grant 95-69, $100,000, to complete the reinstallation of the European Collections.
  - The Philadelphia Orchestra Association, 95-116, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1809
    Grant 95-116, $50,000, for a "Magic of Music" planning grant for the Video Enhancement Project to test the use of video screens in the concert hall.
  - The Phillips Collection, 95-82, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1818
    Grant 95-82, $50,000, for the development, presentation and national tour of the exhibition, "Arthur Dove, Marsden Hartley, John Marin, Georgia O'Keeffe, and Alfred Stieglitz: In the American Grain.
  - Saint Paul Riverfront Corporation, 95-77, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1825
    Grant 95-77, $150,000, to purchase a permanent tent and staging equipment for use as an outdoor performance facility on St. Paul's riverfront.
  - St. Paul Chamber Orchestra Society, 95-117, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 2026
    Grant 95-117, $50,000, for a Magic of Music planning grant to pilot a new concert product that includes additional elements such as theater, literature, video, works of art and conversation
  - Symphony Society of San Antonio, 95-118, 1995 April 18-1996 April 18 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2027
    Grant 95-118, $50,000, for a Magic of Music planning grant for the research and development of "Casual Classics" an interactive concert series.
  - American Academy in Rome, 94-78, 1994 March 23-1996 March 23 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1267
    Grant 94-78, $250,000, to initiate the Southeastern Regional Visiting Artists Program, the foremost American overseas center for independent study and advanced research in the fine arts and humanities.
  - Arden Theatre Company, 95-207, 1995 September 20-1997 September 20 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1280
    Grant 95-207, $100,000.00, for operating support to provide artistic stability during a major capital campaign and transition to a new facility. For artistic operating support during the first two transition seasons.
  - Colorado Symphony Association, 96-311, 1996 December 10-1997 December 10 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1923
    Grant 96-311, for a "Magic of Music" planning grant to develop "Explore the Music, a three year initiative focusing on innovative outreach programming, interactive, multimedia concert series and a survey of community cultural needs.
  - Detroit Historical Society, 95-206, 1995 September 20-1997 September 20 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1333
    Grant 95-206, $50,000.00, for "Motor City," a permanent exhibition that interprets the history of Detroit as the automotive capital of the world, which is the major component of a larger "History in the Making" capital campaign.
  - Kansas City Symphony, 96-310, 1996 December 10-1997 December 10 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 2032
    Grant 96-310, $50,000, for a Magic of Music planning grant to present "Concert Connections" a musician-led initiative focused on attracting audiences ro rhe orchestra's main programming.
  - Lexington Philharmonic Society Inc., 96-103, 1996 June 18-1997 June 18 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 2033
    Grant 96-103, $10,000, to continue and expand the concert series, "Unplugged and Untied" in the 1996-1997 season.
  - Louisiana Philharmonic Orchestra, 96-312, 1996 December 10-1997 December 10 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2034
    Grant 96-312, $50,000, for a Magic of Music planning grant for "Connections" a series of activities aimed at transforming presentation of its concert programming, and to present a pilot concert which incorporates new techniques.
  - Michigan Opera Theatre, 95-237, 1995 September 20-1997 September 20 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1447
    Grant 95-237, $70,000.00, for annual support of education and outreach programs in 1995-1996, and for alternative fall programming, and for communitywide activities leading up and including the inaugural week celebration of the new Detroit Opera House.
  - New World Symphony Inc., 94-71, 1994 March 23-1997 March 23 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1481
    Grant 94-71, $300,000.00, for a new contemporary music initiative designed to expand the national profile of this career-training orchestra. To enhance the training program and its national reputation both for recruiting and development purposes.
  - North Carolina Performing Arts Center at Charlotte Foundation, 95-164, 1995 June 20-1997 June 20 (Box 38, Folder 1-2)
    Knight File Number - 1811
    Grant 95-164, $430,000, for full implementation of an in-house marketing agency to serve Opera Carolina, North Carolina Dance Theatre, Charlotte Repertory Theatre, and the Performing Arts Center.
  - Opera American Inc., 94-331, 1996 December 14-1997 December 14 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1806
    Grant 94-331, $225,000, for the Subsequent Production Initiative to encourage the producation of recent, but neglected, American operas.
  - Opera San Jose Inc., 95-23, 1996 April 18-1997 April 18 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1785
    Grant 95-23, $75,000, to purchase and make capital improvements to a facility that consolidates the opera's operations.
  - Philadelphia Orchestra Association, 96-174, 1996 June 18-1997 June 18 (Box 38, Folder 5-6)
    Knight File Number - 2035
    Grant 96-174, $390,000, for a Magic of Music implementation project to continue testing the Video Enhancement Project in 1996-97 at the Academy of Music and the Mann Center. 2 folders.
  - Public Radio International, 94-334, 1994 December 14-1997 December 14 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1822
    Grant 94-334, $200,000, to develop new classical music programming for public radio to appeal to younger, culturally diverse listeners and to develop ancillary educational materials.
  - Southern Arts Federation Inc., 95-182, 1995 June 20-1997 June 20 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1823
    Grant 95-182, $90,000, to extend the Folk Arts Traveling Exhibit Program for two additional years.
  - The Village of Arts and Humanities Inc., 95-147, 1995 June 20-1997 June 20 (Box 39, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1773
    Grant 95-147, $40,000, for educational programs at this community-based arts organization in North Philadelphia.
  - The Washington Drama Society Inc., 94-330, 1994 December 14-1997 December 14 (Box 39, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1763